A Guide to the Henry Smals Papers, 1871-1891
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Henry Smals Papers 1871-1891
Special Collections, James Madison University
2059
1 and 1/2 Hollinger boxes and 1 separate container; .68 linear feet
The Henry Smals Papers, 1871-1891, consist of one and one-half Hollinger boxes and one separate container of diaries written by Henry Smals of Bridgewater, Va. The topics of diary entries are brief outlining day-to-day activities. A folder, located in Box 3, contains a partial index and a list of highlights for most volumes as well as an ad for "Henry Smals, Fashionable Barber! Main Street, Bridgewater, Va."
Henry Smals
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
The collection is on deposit from the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society.
Biographical Information
Henry Smals (1810-1892) is listed in the 1850 Rockingham County Census as a shoemaker with real estate value of $1,000 with a wife, Mary, and six children. There is an entry for Henry Smalts in the 1860 census and for Henry Smalls in the 1870 census that gives additional household details. He may also have been a barber sometime during the 1880s (ses Box 3, Folder 4). His surname appears as a variation of Smalz and Smaltz as well.
Scope and Content
The Henry Smals Papers, 1871-1891, consist of one and one-half Hollinger boxes and one separate container of eighteen volumes of diaries written by Henry Smals of Bridgewater, Va. the topics of diary entries are brief outlining day-to-day activities. There are mentions of acquaintances that are ill, various business transactions conducted in town, the movement of livestock, and hay through town, ongoing town projects, churcch activities, marriages, births, deaths, and other details of town life. The activities of "colored people" are occasionally noted. Throughout the diaries, Smals made small drawings of people and animals and added illustrations cclipped from newspapers. A folder, located in Box 3, contains printed copies of a partial index and a list of highlights for most columes as well as an ad for "Henry Smals, Fashionable Barber! Main Street, Bridgewater, Va."
Arrangement
The diaries are arranged chronologically where possible, but due to variations in size are physically housed as follows in the Contents List. Volume 14 is filed in a separate container.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
United States Census Office, 7th census. 1850 U.S. Census, Rockingham County, Virginia. Wichita, Ks.: S-K Publications, 1987.
Contents List
- Henry Smals Diaries 1871-1891
  - Vol.1: May 1871-June 1872 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Vol.2: July 1872-Dec. 1872 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Vol.3: Jan. 1873-Aug. 1873 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Vol.4: Aug. 1873-Jan. 1875 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Vol.5: Jan. 1875-Nov. 1875 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Vol.6: Jan. 1876-April 1877 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Vol.7: April 1877-Sept. 1877; incl. Dec. 1873, 1875; Jan. and Nov. 1875 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Vol.8: Oct. 1877-April 1878 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Vol.9: May 1878-Jan. 1879 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Vol.10: Feb. 1879-Oct. 1879 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Vol.11: Oct. 1879-May 1880 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Vol.12: May 1880-Jan. 1881 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Vol.13: Jan. 1881-Nov. 1881 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Vol.14: Nov. 1881-May 1883 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Vol.15: May 1883-July 1885 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Vol.16: July 1885- April 1887 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Vol.17: April 1887-April 1890 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Vol.18: April 1890-Oct. 1891 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Index and Highlights (Box-folder 3:4)